Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is ל"ח lamed chet
and we pick up on the משנה mishna ל"ד עמוד ב. lamed
dalet amud bet. Okay, so the משנה mishna at the bottom there,
and now we are starting, we've been dealing with some תיקון עולם
tikkun olam things that were connected to גיטין, Gittin, and now we're
going to turn to תיקון עולם tikkun olam things for the betterment
of the world that are not limited to גיטין. Gittin. Obviously right
now the betterment of the world has a very sort of local
meaning, right? It's to make it that this woman isn't left an
עגונה agunah or doesn't think she's divorced when she's not divorced, or
doesn't have people challenge her גט get incorrectly.
So you could speak about sort of a more systematic because we
want to obviously protect all women in this type of situation, but
nevertheless it's interesting who's the עולם olam that we're being מתקן, metakken,
right? And what exactly is the nature of that תיקון? tikkun? So
because
תיקון עולם tikkun olam is obviously a phrase that's used in other
contexts, you know for like broad universal social justice, and so far
here it's being used to protect people against הלכה halachic abuse let's
say, or about being like about הלכה halacha putting them
in a difficult
situation, particularly to protect the woman from people incorrectly challenging the גט
get or things she's divorced when she's not. So let's see what
the next example now that we begin to broaden it of תיקון
עולם tikkun olam is. אין אלמנה נפרעת מנכסי יתומים אלא בשבועה. Ain
almonah nifra'as mi'nechasei yesomim ela bishvuah. An אלמנה, almonah, a widow, cannot
collect from the property of the heirs of the orphans except with
a שבועה. shvuah. So here's a woman, her husband died, her כתובה
kesubah allows her to either stay on the estate and live on
the estate and continue to be supported, you know room and board,
or if she wants to like sort of separate herself from her
previous husband's estate, go off on her own, then she can collect
her lump sum כתובה kesubah payment which is the מאתיים זוז. matayim
zuz. So she now wants to go ahead and collect that lump
sum כתובה kesubah payment, so she has to take an oath to
the heirs that none of the כתובה kesubah had been prepaid during
her lifetime. Okay, so that's the הלכה. halacha.
נמנעו מלהשביע, Nimne'u mil'hashbia, but the problem is is that they stopped
making her take an oath because the consequence of a שבועת שקר
shvuas sheker was very very severe, and they were concerned that people,
as we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara, would make oaths falsely, not
intentionally but nevertheless it would occur, and we'll see that they were
afraid that that would be too prevalent and therefore they didn't make
her take an oath. Of course that didn't do her any good
because by not letting her take an oath they also weren't letting
her collect, so she was really stuck. So they're too פרום frum
to let her take an oath, but then she's stuck without being
able to collect. So התקין רבן גמליאל הזקן שתהא נודרת ליתומים כל
מה שירצו וגובה כתובתה. hitchkin Rabban Gamliel hazaken shetehei noderes liyesomim kol
mah sheyirtzu vegova kesubasah. So Rabban Gamliel the elder established she'll take
a vow to the orphans whatever they want and she'll collect her
כתובה. kesubah. She pays off through a נדר, neder, she could say
if you remember from נדרים, nedarim, rather than an oath like if
I'm lying, you know taking an oath in the name of God
that you're telling the truth, which is like bringing God as witness
to bear witness to the truth of your statement, and that's you
know the פסוק pasuk that says לא ינקה ה' את אשר ישא
שמו לשוא. lo yinakeh Hashem es asher yisa shemo lashav. God will
not cleanse the person who takes His name in vain. So that's
really sort of invoking the name of God to attest to the
veracity of your statement. A נדר neder is very different. A נדר
neder doesn't invoke God at all and a נדר neder basically just
says that this object is forbidden like a sort of like a
קרבן korban is forbidden. Okay, so what they would do is they
would shift to the world of נדרים nedarim and therefore it
would satisfy their concern for the veracity of her statement but they
would not be concerned about
the severe consequences if it was false. And what she would basically
say was if
I had any of my כתובה kesubah prepaid
until this point then all of the fruit in the world will
be forbidden to me. Okay, so it's not an oath, it's just
making the food forbidden. But then so the consequence will be to
now have to live her life without eating any fruit, and fruit
probably has a broader meaning
about any produce.
So obviously it'll have very severe consequences so they can assume she's
telling the truth, but it will not be a שבועת שוא. shvuas
shav. So כל מה שירצו kol mah sheyirtzu meaning the orphans can
pick, now maybe it wouldn't be something as impossible as going through
your life without ever eating any produce, but they can pick whatever
they
want. Take a נדר neder of X that you will never get
any benefit from object X Y and
Z if you're lying and then you can go ahead and collect
your כתובה. kesubah. Okay,
so that's number two תיקון עולם, tikkun olam, although we haven't said
תיקון עולם tikkun olam but that's going to be the wrap-up statement
at the end of the משנה. mishna.
Another תיקון עולם, tikkun olam, העדים חותמין על הגט מפני תיקון עולם.
Ha'eiddim chosmin al haget mipnei tikkun olam. The witnesses sign on a
גט get for the sake of תיקון עולם. tikkun olam. So that's
something that we've been quoting a lot which basically means to allow
the woman to remarry without having to produce the witnesses that were
physically present. That's the position of רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, that biblically
you do not need witnesses to sign, you needed it rabbinically, but
that allows her to remarry. And הלל התקין פרוזבול מפני תיקון עולם.
Hillel hitkin Pruzbul mipnei Tikkun Olam. הלל Hillel established a פרוזבול Pruzbul
for the sake of תיקון עולם. Tikkun Olam. It is interesting that
the word תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam did not exactly appear by the
case of the אלמנה. Almana. Obviously it's implicit, התקין רבן גמליאל, hitkin
Rabban Gamliel, but it never actually says מפני תיקון עולם. mipnei Tikkun
Olam.
Okay. So anyway, so you have all these things of תיקון עולם.
Tikkun Olam. Again, who is the עולם Olam that we are being
מתקן? metaken? In one case it's the widows, okay, I mean, the
previous case was the woman being divorced, in one case it's the
widows, here again is a woman being divorced, and in the final
case it is the whole need to borrow money. Is it the
lenders? Is it the
borrowers? He's talking about also a very broad sort of societal reality
of how money is going to be borrowed and paid back. Okay,
but the עולם Olam still is the Jewish עולם, Olam, you know,
the עולם. Olam. When you say the עולם, Olam, okay, so you're
not talking about the עולם, Olam, the עולם. Olam. Anyway, but
anyway, let's keep— and also it's interesting to see the natures of
the תיקונים. Tikunim. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מאי
איריא אלמנה? Mai irya Almana? Why you say that an אלמנה Almana
can't collect from the orphans without an oath? Anybody who's coming to
collect from orphans has to take an oath 'cause the father isn't
alive to swear that to— I mean maybe the father paid up
and there's a— and he lost the receipt or the guy trust—
or the guy trusted him or he trusted the guy rather, excuse
me, not to have to produce a receipt. And if the father
was alive, he would have said, "What do you mean I owe
you a hundred dollars? I paid you up." Okay. So what do
we do? Somebody's coming to collect a debt, the father isn't alive,
he has an IOU, how do we defend the interests of the
heirs? So the general rule is that anybody who comes to collect
a debt after the principal's dead and is coming to collect it
from the heirs has to take an oath. So why did the
משנה Mishna say an אלמנה, Almana, a widow, has to take an
oath when she's coming to collect her כתובה? Kesuba? Should have said
anybody who's coming to collect a debt. Even though the תקנה Takana
was for the אלמנה, Almana, start by saying anybody has to take
an oath who's coming to collect from the heirs, but then they
stopped having the אלמנה Almana take the oath and therefore they established
this תקנה. Takana. So why did they just focus on the אלמנה,
Almana, the widow's need to take an oath? אפילו כולי עלמא נמי
דהא קיימא לן הבא ליפרע מנכסי יתומים לא יפרע אלא בשבועה. Afilu
kulei alma nami deha kayma lan haba lipara minechasei yesomim lo yipara
ela bishvua. If somebody is coming to collect from the property of
the heirs, of the orphans, he doesn't collect unless he takes an
oath that the debt hadn't been paid up. So אלמנה איצטריכא ליה.
Almana itztricha lei. It wanted to underscore that even an אלמנה, Almana,
the הלכה Halacha used to be, had to take an oath. סלקא
דעתך אמינא, Salka daatach amina, I would have thought, משום חינא אקילו
בה רבנן גביה, mishum china akilu bah Rabbanan gabeih, because of חן,
chen, of charm, of finding favor, the rabbis were lenient by her.
What does that mean? It
doesn't mean oh, she's a woman we go easy on them or
something like that. It means that because this was related to the
institution of marriage, and because anybody who would get married, you know,
they wanted the כתובה Kesuba available, obviously the whole point of the
כתובה Kesuba was in order that they would be able to collect
if they were left widowed. You might have thought that the rabbis
might have said, "Look, in order to encourage women to marry, right,
and not to be concerned that they won't be protected, or maybe
whether it's an incentive to marry or whether it's just in general
to ensure that women are protected with the כתובה, Kesuba, we have
to go easy and not and not demand that they make a
שבועה. shvua. We have to do this to benefit the women that
they will— that this כתובה Kesuba will really protect their interests or
that they'll trust that the כתובה Kesuba will protect their interests and
so they'll marry." Okay, and therefore we might— I might have thought
that for that reason they would not have to make a שבועה
shvua when they went to— when they went to collect their כתובה,
Kesuba, קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, that they did not say
that. So if you look at רש"י: Rashi: משום חינא שיהא חן
הנשים בעיני האנשים לינשא להם, mishum china sheyehei chen hanashim beeinei haanashim
linasei lahem, that women would be prepared— prepared to marry. It's an
interesting question actually, right, like who do you have to incentivize to
get married?
So is it the men that have to be incentivized because they
just want to remain single? Is it the women because they can't
trust that their financial interests are being taken care of? Anyway, but
the גמרא Gemara does sometimes say that there's this issue of משום
חינא, mishum china, okay, that maybe we need to, you know, and
again, it could be read as to incentivize women to marry or
it could be said to ensure that their interests are protected. So
it didn't start that way. It started by saying a woman when
she collects her כתובה Kesuba is like anybody else who's coming to
collect from the heirs and has to make a שבועה. shvua. But
then they realized that because people were being פרום frum and saying,
"Uh-oh, we don't want her to take a שבועה, shvua, maybe she'll
take a false שבועה," shvua, she was really hurt by the fact
that she didn't even have an option, a way of collecting her
כתובה Kesuba 'cause they won't let her take a שבועה. shvua. So
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel made this institution of the נדר. Neder. Yes?
What— when we— maybe also be worried that if the כתובה Kesuba
is just to collect after he dies, that she's going to be
trying to convince him to divorce her, isn't that kind of— like
what the כתובה Kesuba is for?
Well, maybe.
I don't know. I mean, that's a little— I—
that would be, I mean, given that the man has all of
the power, unilateral power, I mean, it is true there are some
times where a concern that she might try to make his life
so miserable. But then it also— look, it's— yeah, I'm not sure.
Anyway it could be but I think that that's like a little
bit more of a a little more of a far-fetched scenario because
it's not like when she then tries to collect the כתובה Ksuba
even if he's alive although she might have to make a שבועה
Shvuah but he can still make a counter-claim you know so
I don't see that as more as the immediate thing to be
concerned about. All right נימנעו מלהשביע Nimnu milahashvia so they so then
what they stop but then they stopped taking her take an oath.
So they we'll see they were afraid she would make a false
oath and we'll see why maybe it was particularly a concern about
widows why did they let other people make oaths? So the גמרא
Gemara says מאי טעמא Mai Ta'ama what's the reason? אילימא משום דרב
כהנא אמר רב Ilima mishum d'Rav Kahana amar Rav maybe it's because
of the story of רב כהנא Rav Kahana אמר רב כהנא Amar
Rav Kahana excuse me רב כהנא Rav Kahana ואמרי לה אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב V'amri lei amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav מעשה באשה
אחת בשני בצורת Ma'aseh b'isha achas bishnei batzores there
was a story about a certain man in the time of famine
שהפקיד דינר זהב אצל אלמנה she'hifkid dinar zahav etzel almanah
that he left a this wasn't even a case of the husband
I think it seems to be a normal man just how to
widow right I mean it couldn't be the husband leaving it by
the widow. A normal man left by the widow a gold coin
to watch on his behalf והניחתו בכד של קמח v'hiniachto b'kad shel
kemach and she put it in a in you know a pitcher
of flour ואפתו בפת v'afto b'pas and then
there's a it's going to see accidentally she forgot about it it
was a great hiding place so great of a hiding place that
she forgot about it and then she baked it into bread. I
don't know how she didn't feel it as she was kneading the
dough but okay. How big is a דינר? dinar? I mean we
know we have Roman denarii are they big? Are they small? Anybody
know?
Charlie where's Charlie? Okay ונתנתו לעני v'nesnatu l'ani and then because it
because it was a period of famine presumably that's the context of
it being a period of famine she gave this loaf of bread
to an עני. ani. לימים בא בעל הדינר L'yamim ba ba'al hadinar
then the person who entrusted the דינר dinar came there ואמר לה
v'amar lah said to her הבו לי דינרי havu li dinari give
me my דינר. dinar. אמרה לו Amrah lo she said to him
she said look I can't find it I don't know what happened
to it but יהנה סם המות באחד מבניה של אותה אשה yehaneh
sam hamaves b'echad mibaneha shel osa isha
poison should be effective or you know should work one of the
children of that woman meaning one of my children right should succumb
to
poison אם נהנית מדינרך כלום im neheness midinaracha klum if I got
any benefit out of your דינר. dinar. I'm promising you I did
not steal it I didn't do anything with it I don't know
what happened to it I can't find it okay it was a
case I guess that she was a שומר חינם shomer chinam she's
exempt from גניבה ואבידה gneiva v'aveida she said she lost it all
right whether that was negligence or not we'll see but anyway but
she's taking an oath that she derived no benefit from it. אמרו
Amru
they
said לא היו ימים מועטים lo hayu yamim muatim it was not
too long עד שמת אחד מבניה ad shemes echad mibaneha one of
her children died. Now how did she benefit from it? We'll see
in a minute. וכששמעו חכמים בדבר Uch'shesham'u chachamim badavar and when the
sages heard the matter אמרו amru and they said מה מי שנשבע
באמת כך mah mi shenishba be'emes kach somebody who swore truthfully look
at the consequences הנשבע על שקר על אחת כמה וכמה hanishba al
sheker al achas kama v'chama how much more so somebody who intentionally
swears falsely what the consequences will be by taking a false oath.
So מאי טעמא איענשה? mai ta'ama i'anesha? Now the גמרא Gemara wants
to figure this out why was she punished? I mean she actually
did not benefit from it. So the גמרא's Gemara answering is דאשתרשי
לה מקום דינר. d'ishtareshi lah makom dinar. No she benefited because she
benefited from the volume that the דינר dinar took up in the
bread. And the double irony is she didn't even eat the bread
herself she gave the bread to an עני. ani. So like what
benefit did she
get? It's like she didn't give extra stuff away but it was
her complete decision to give it away.
Did she not get even for that? She did not get the
benefit of like you know עולם הבא Olam Haba of צדקה tzedakah
somehow
like you know giving to an עני ani like you know? I
don't know okay that no we don't consider the מצוה mitzvah benefit
a benefit for these things. Okay so anyway so that was the
benefit. So then the גמרא Gemara says ומי מי שנשבע באמת? umi
mi shenishba be'emes? So then if that explains why she was punished
why does it say Look if somebody who swore truthfully had this
happen to them? But it wasn't a truthful oath your whole point
was that actually it was a false oath. גמרא Gemara says okay
כמי שנשבע באמת k'mi shenishba be'emes it was as if it was
truthful. In her mind she was swearing truthfully. So somebody who's intending
to swear truthfully and accidentally you know made a mistake and said
something wrong and swore falsely and it gets such a severe punishment
how much more so someone who intends to swear falsely. So now
the גמרא Gemara says now of course the problem with this is
that if that's the reason why you don't make her take an
oath why do you make anyone take an oath? Right? Why did
they continue to allow you know men to take oaths? So the
גמרא's Gemara going to say why did they continue to allow women
who are גרושות grushos to take oaths? Like why? Because the case
was an אלמנה almanah all of a sudden we see that this
is going to be a problem with אלמנות? almanos? So we'll see
in a minute that it might have uniquely to do with the
relationship of the אלמנה almanah to her dead husband. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this or to the heirs. So let's take a
look.
טורח Torach and right exactly okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this אי משום הא ei mishum
ha if
that was the reason they didn't make her take an oath מהירי
אלמנה mai irya almanah why specifically an אלמנה? almanah? אפילו גרושה נמי
Afilu grusha nami even a גרושה. grusha. I could have said even
any person. אלא אמר רב זירא אמר שמואל Ela amar Rav Zeira
amar Shmuel why did רב זירא Rav Zeira say in the name
of שמואל? Shmuel? לא שנו. Lo shanu. אלמנה almana *almanah*, the only
person that they had said couldn't take an oath was an אלמנה
almanah *almanah*, אבל גרושה grushah משביעין לה *aval gerushah mashbinan lah*, but
a גרושה grushah, *gerushah* they would? What difference would it be? Maybe
we're afraid they'll swear falsely because then intentionally or unintentionally that they
really would have some of the כתובה kesuvah *ksuba* paid up and
they'll have forgotten about it or they'll be lying. So must be
no, אלמנה almanah. שאני *almanah shani*, אלמנה almanah *almanah* is different that
we had a real concern, דבי היא נא דקטרחא קמי דיתמי *debei
hi na dekatarcha kmei dyasmei*, because she you know she she exerts
effort for the orphans, there she is, she's in her her dead
husband's home, she's living with her kids, and you know she's doing
favors for them. She's cooking, she's cleaning, nobody's paying her for that,
okay. I mean you could say some of that has to do
with the כתובה kesuvah. *ksuba* arrangement, but now whatever doesn't matter, obviously
she's going to be helping out at the house in ways that
she's not obligated for, and therefore, אתיא לאורויי היתירא *atya loraei heteira*,
she'll come to rationalize and herself and she'll come to actually take
some money in payment of the כתובה kesuvah *ksuba* and tell herself
that she's allowed to. Now, does that mean that she actually would
consciously say I'm going to go to my you know oh I
found a hundred dollars here in my husband's room I'll just take
it as payment of the כתובה kesuvah. *ksuba* but I'm allowed to
have my כתובה kesuvah. *ksuba* paid up because or whatever? Now if
that's the case it's hard to imagine that then she's going to
swear you know that she didn't have her כתובה kesuvah, *ksuba* paid
up she consciously knows that she took money in payment of her
כתובה kesuvah *ksuba*. But that's presumably the point is that it's not
that conscious. Like you basically say oh look here's 20 bucks, you
know what I've been working so hard I owe myself like a
nice a nice lunch out and you take the money and take
a lunch out. Now why would you know that was your dead
husband's money, what does that mean that you took 20 dollars and
you spent it on yourself? Right, so that's that's defined as taking
money towards the כתובה kesuvah. *ksuba* payment. You took money that belonged
to the dead husband's estate, it wasn't coming to you, you spent
it on yourself, so in you know your mind it's like man
I've been working so hard I deserve to go out for a
cup of coffee and you took the money right? So and then
you take an oath that like I didn't benefit any from any
of my dead husband's property. So in your own mind it's exactly
like this case in your own mind you don't you think it's
true.
Right and never from someone else either because
well okay so the point is it's true. So we have to
be able to balance that. We need to allow her to collect,
we need to allow her to take an oath, but we don't
want to deal with the severe consequences of a שבועה shvua, *shvua*.
So you know that's sort of the middle ground. But it seems
that it's unique to if I'm just a creditor and I'm taking
an oath to the orphans, right, I'm what's the scenario in which
I took some money pocketed some money and I rationalized it and
in my mind I think I didn't do anything wrong, right? There
isn't a scenario. In a גרושה grushah *gerushah* there isn't an אלמנה
almanah *almanah* there's a common scenario. So although the original case where
this dinar and the bread happened to be an אלמנה almanah. *almanah*
and her status as אלמנה almanah. *almanah* was pretty irrelevant to the
story, but the ongoing the concern is that an אלמנה almanah, *almanah*
will you know will have taken some money from the estate, rationalized
it like you know people at work you know they take home
you know a pen or whatever a pad of paper you know
and they rationalize. So it's the same type of a concern and
that's why they had to stop making a שבועה shvua *shvua*. Yes
Dov.
All the way through from כתובות *Ksubot* all the way through the
working marriage seems to very much be clearly like it's his money
or her money. Right,
it's really not I mean do people today
structure their marriages that way commonly? No, right it's really a different
yeah I mean sure the whole economics of marriage was completely different.
The husband was the provider, the wife I mean it was an
old-fashioned marriage. The husband was the provider, it was his money, the
wife was the housekeeper and the one who raised the children and
she was living off of his money and for in his house
and that's what the whole כתובה kesuvah. *ksuba* was about. Not so
basic.
I mean to say out loud right yeah. Yep have to I
mean did you see the article about the Upper East Side wives
with the the bonuses? No, the marriage bonuses. Yeah yeah like look
at it a several months ago like an article came out about
a tell-all about Upper East Side wives and like you know...
His money her money.
Right and she gets bonuses if she does a good job that
year.
Oh my god wow.
Unusual
though I think but in unusual though.
Okay so that's
anyway anyway yeah.
But
if you really have concern about financial malfeasance why not just make
her submit a general ledger in addition to the נדר nedar *neder*
or שבועה shvua. *shvua*?
In other words these are my הוצאות *hotzaot* and this is what
I you know collected in other words
she should give him a ledger.
She should require her to. In other words really worried you know
because she's going to rationalize she's going to say oh well you
know.
I think look I think you raise a good question I think
like that gets to the תיקון עולם tikkun olam? *tikkun olam* question
like what's a type of an institution that the society could manage
to require every woman not everybody man or woman whatever you know
is good with numbers or you know can be responsible to state
whatever you. Right you don't it's not like you have a business
you're just a housekeeper all of a sudden you require everybody. So
I think the question is that you know what's reasonable to have
everybody take an oath and then you can collect.
But but my problem is she's going to take a נדר neder?
*neder* or. I get your problem you know no no solution's going
to solve every case. Now take there are two quick תוספות Tosafos
*Tosfots*. תוספות Tosafos. *Tosfot* says on the first one, לא היו ימים
מועטין *lo hayu yamim muatin*. תוספות Tosafos *Tosfot* says, ואם תאמר *ve'im
tomar* מאי טעם העונש *mai taam hayonash* כדאמרינן *karmina* בפרק המדיר *perek
hamadir* שבועות Shvuos *shvuos* האדם בש... *haadam bish...* בשבועה פרט לאונס כדרב
כהנא ורב כהנא דממשתבע בהכי אמר רב Rav וממשתבע בהכי אמר רב.
Rav. So basically תוספות Tosafos. points out that there's a גמרא Gemara
that says that when you take an oath and you think you're
telling the truth, it's not a שבועת שקר. shvuas sheker. If in
your mind you're telling the truth, the גמרא Gemara says you don't
transgress, okay? So it's not like you transgressed בשוגג. bishogeg. She didn't
transgress, she thought she was telling the truth. All right, so skip
to the end of תוספות. Tosafos. It goes through the whole thing
and then three lines from the end תוספות Tosafos says, ויש לומר
דהכא גבי פקדון היה לו להזהר יותר לשמרו היטב ראוי לאסוקי אדעתיה
שתבא לידי שבועה. veyesh lomar dehacha gabei pikadon haya lo lehizahar yoser
leshomro heytev rauei lasukei adaitya shetavo lidei shvua. Now here it was
entrusted to her safekeeping, so she had a heightened responsibility. So since
she was negligent, okay, even though it's interesting like she thought she
was telling the truth, but since she was negligent in her mistake,
okay, therefore it's not like the situation was outside of my control
because like if I genuinely, honestly think it, okay, you honestly think
it but you're negligent in the reason you have that belief, right?
You should have... there's reasons that you shouldn't have that belief, so
you weren't taking enough care to have the right information. So anyway,
that's very interest... yeah?
Don't we learn anything besides שבועת אונס? shvuat ones?
Yeah, well that's the גמרא Gemara in נדרים Nedarim and שבועות but
we didn't... but anyway, but I'm not having that conversation. I just
want to point out תוספות. Tosafos, Okay, anyway.
Okay, so now the next one is דמאי יהא היתרה. demai yehei
heteira. Look at this next תוספות. Tosafot ולכך נמנעו מלהשביעה בשבועה מרובה,
ulekach nimneu milehashpiasha bishvua meruba, right?
Because the גמרא Gemara doesn't quote it here, but it's implicit in
the story, but it's like לא ינקה השם את אשר ישא שמו
לשוא. lo yenake Hashem es asher yisa shemo lashav. It's very weighty
שבועה, shvua okay? And then he says אלא בהדרה דלא חמיר כולי
האי, ela behadara delo chamir kuli hai, and נדר neder isn't so
weighty. והשתא בזמן הזה תקנו לקבל חרם במקום שבועה שלא יהא המכשול
כל כך. vehashata bizman hazeh tiknu lekabel cherem bemakom shvua shelo yehei
hamichshol kol kach. If somebody has to testify or swear to something
in court in general, right? So this is the question, why only
the woman? So this leads to a greater, you know, sort of
reservation or fear of anybody taking a שבועה shvua, because any honest
mistake, although תוספות Tosafot deals with the fact that if you genuinely
believe it's true, but any negligent, any type of a mistake that's
not completely faultless
is very, very severe consequences. So they had people take a חרם,
cherem, right? Which is basically like, you know, like
God should curse me type of a thing. That sounds pretty harsh.
Right, but again it's not the real consequences as the שבועה. shvua
All right, now that by the way that's important because I'm seeing
I assume people are aware of the fact that, you know, for
like hundreds of years if not, you know, more,
if not like a thousand years, you know, Jews were very... why
does when a Jew goes to court, you know, they say do
you affirm as opposed to do you swear, right? Because there are
deep-seated, you know, sort of recoil from taking a שבועה shvua even
a שבועת אמת. shvuas emes.
What do they actually do in a בית דין beis din now?
If they really go.
I don't know, they don't do שבועה, shvua okay? They might do
חרם, cherem, I'm not sure exactly, I don't know. Okay, but anyway
but this is sourced in like this גמרא, Gemara, okay? It started
with the אלמנה almanah but logically then it should be about anyone.
Okay, so תוספות, Tosafot now why don't they do נדר? neder. Maybe
for your reason נדר neder, also, but, you know, but anyway we
move away from שבועה shvua, even a שבועת אמת. shvuas emes. Okay,
so that's... so that's very important in terms of that principle. So
now the other thing I wanted to say which is interesting is,
you know, it's a difference between a שבועה shvua. and an אלה.
ala. We sort of had this by סוטה, sotah, right? A שבועה
shvua is just I swear that I'm telling the truth, period. An
אלה ala is if I'm lying, let God curse me, let this
bad thing happen to me. Right? The only quote language that she
used was really language of an אלה, ala, right? That if I'm
lying let my son, you know, die of poison or something like
that. She didn't take an oath to say I'm telling the truth.
Presumably that preceded it, but it is interesting, are we talking about
a שבועה, shvua. are we talking about an אלה? ala? It does
seem, you know, here they're sort of not distinguishing between the two.
They say it's שבועה. shvuah They're saying it's a שבועה shvuah but
the quote does not have the language of a שבועה. shvuah Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, where are we? אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב אמר רב ירמיה בר אבא רב ושמואל דאמרי
תרווייהו, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav amar Rav Yirmiya bar Abba Rav
uShmuel damri tarvaihu, Rav and Shmuel both say, לא שנו אלא בבית
דין. lo shanu ela beveis din. When is this true that we
don't make her take an oath? Only in the court. אבל חוץ
לבית דין משבינן לה. aval chutz leveis din mashpinan lah. We can
make her take an oath outside of the court. Now what difference
does it make? I mean if the concern is about the heavy
consequences of an oath, so why should we be prepared to do
it out of the court? So if you look at רש״י Rashi
about eight lines from the narrow lines at the top, חוץ לבית
דין משבינן לה, chutz leveis din mashpinan lah, רש״י Rashi says ששבועת
הדיינים של תורה היא ונוקט ספר תורה בידו או תפילין ומשביע לה
בשמו או בכינויו כדאשכחן באברהם שים נא ידך תחת ירכי והשבעתיך בהשם
ועונשם מרובה. sheshvuat hadayanin shel Torah hi venoket sefer Torah beyado o
tefillin umashpia lah bishmo o bekinuyo kidashkachan beAvraham sim na yadecha tachas
yerechi vehishvacha baShem veonasham meruba. So in בית דין beis din it's
like you use a ספר תורה, sefer Torah, you hold onto it
and you use God's name and it's very weighty.
וחוץ לבית דין שבועה דרבנן היא בכללה וארור. vechutz leveis din shvua
derabbanan hi biklala vearur. So that's like the case of the woman.
You don't take an oath in the name of God, you just
say let me, you know, let me be cursed or whatever. לא
נקט מידי, v'lo nakat midi, you don’t hold on to a ספר
תורה, Sefer Torah, ואין עונשו כל כך, v'ein onsho kol kach, and
it’s not as severe.
So that sounds and that
sounds like the case of the of the son, but maybe that
was right exactly. So let’s see what the גמרא Gemara does with
it. Okay, so you have different things for those are three different,
so two different interesting things, whether you’re holding on to a ספר
תורה, Sefer Torah, you know, or some holy object and whether you
invoke God’s name or not. Okay, so now let’s go back and
then תוספות Tosafot has a whole discussion about is it difference between
דאורייתא de'Oraisa or דרבנן de'Rabbanan in בית דין Beis Din and out
of בית דין. Beis Din. Anyway, let’s take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says אבל חוץ לבית דין משביעין אותה, aval chutz l'Beis
Din mashbi'in osah, we would be prepared to do it. איני? eini?
Is this true? והא רב לא מגבי כתובה לארמלתא. v'ha Rav lo
magbi kesuvah l'armalta. רב Rav refused to collect the כתובה kesuvah for
an אלמנה almanah because we’ll see it’s against the משנה, Mishnah, we’ll
see, but he felt that you couldn’t even have her take a
נדר. neder, So once he wasn't having her take a נדר, neder?
he couldn't have her collect, we'll see, he and now of course
that's obviously terrible, she's left without her כתובה. kesuvah, We'll get to
that. But the גמרא Gemara says but why didn't according to this
why didn't he just have her take a שבועה shvuah outside of
בית דין? Beis Din? גמרא Gemara says קשיא. kashya. Alright, you’re right,
that’s difficult because this was said in the name and the problem
is that this was said in the name of רב. Rav So
how if רב Rav says you could have her take a שבועה
shvuah out of בית דין, Beis Din, how could רב Rav feel
that there’s times that she won’t be able to collect? Just have
her take a שבועה shvuah out of בית דין. Beis Din. Okay,
so that’s one version where we end in a קשיא. kashya. Then
the גמרא Gemara has another version and says the following:
בסורא מתנו הכי, b'Sura masnu hachi, that's how they taught it in
סורא. Sura. בנהרדעא מתנו הכי, bi'Neharde'a masnu hachi, but in נהרדעא Neharde'a
they teach it the following way.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל: amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: לא שנו
אלא בבית דין. lo shanu ela b'Beis Din. So this is רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda in the name of שמואל. Shmuel. רב Rav is
not part of this statement. אבל חוץ לבית דין משביעין אותה aval
chutz l'Beis Din mashbi'in osah that שמואל Shmuel said you could do
it outside of בית דין. Beis Din. ורב אמר v'Rav amar and
רב Rav disagreed and he said אפילו חוץ לבית דין נמי אין
משביעין אותה, afilu chutz l'Beis Din nami ein mashbi'in osah, you can't
even do a שבועה shvuah. out of בית דין. Beis Din. רב
לטעמיה דרב לא מגבי כתובה לארמלתא Rav l'ta'ameih d'Rav lo magbi kesuvah
l'armalta and רב Rav is consistent because רב Rav wouldn't collect the
כתובה kesuvah for an אלמנה. almanah We'll see why he couldn't use
a נדר, neder but he feels you can't use a שבועה shvuah,
even outside of בית דין. Beis Din. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara finally says okay maybe he felt a שבועה shvuah. in or
out of בית דין Beis Din is off limits, but how about
the נדר? neder תיהדר ותיגביה, teihadar v'sigbei'ah, so make her take a
נדר neder. and collect like our משנה Mishnah says, that was the
whole תקנה. takanah. גמרא Gemara says בשני דרב קילי נדרי. bi'shnei d'Rav
kili nidrei. No, in the time of רב Rav's people treated נדרים
nedarim lightly and therefore he was afraid that either the taking a
נדר neder wouldn't improve anything or that he didn't want her to
transgress and have the punishment of a false נדר. neder So he
felt that a נדר neder? was not a viable option. It didn't
have that right balance of being weighty enough to do the job
and to keep her honest, but not so weighty that the consequences
would be disastrous. And of course the problem is is like she
doesn't get a כתובה. kesuvah Whatever happened to רבן גמליאל? Rabban Gamliel?
Like he didn't feel compelled enough and we're going to see a
few stories like this by the whole impetus of the תקנה takanah
of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel to say whatever I'm going to say,
the whole point of the משנה Mishnah is to teach me that
I have to find a path to make it viable, to make
a woman able to collect a כתובה. kesuvah And the fascinating thing
is that they didn't feel that compulsion. Okay, so let's take a
look at another story. ההיא דאתאי לקמיה דרב הונא, hahi d'asai l'kamei
d'Rav Huna, a woman that came in front of רב הונא. Rav
Huna. אמר לה, amar lah, he said to her, and basically to
collect a כתובה, kesuvah, מאי אעביד לך? mai a'avid lach? Look I
can't help you. דרב לא מגבי כתובה לארמלתא, d'Rav lo magbi kesuvah
l'armalta, רב Rav's wouldn't collect a כתובה kesuvah for an אלמנה and
I'm now going to follow רב's Rav authority. Now that's funny, right?
It sounded like it's no longer that he necessarily shared רב's Rav
opinion, maybe the נדר neder for him would have been a good
enough thing, maybe people were taking נדרים nedarim seriously, but all of
a sudden now רב Rav becomes an authority, right? So it's very
it's an interesting problem, you know the authority of רב Rav is
now getting in the way of this אלמנה and of the whole
concern of רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel.
אמרה ליה, amrah leih, so she said to him, מידי הוא טעמא
אלא דילמא נקיטנא מידי מכתובתי? midi hu ta'ama ela dilma nakisna midi
miksuvasi? Look, your whole concern is that maybe I've already taken collection
of some of my כתובה. kesuvah. חי השם צבאות אם נהניתי מכתובתי
כלום. chai Hashem Tzevaos im nehenesi miksuvasi klum.
By the life of God I did not take anything from my
כתובה. kesuvah. So she took a שבועה. shvuah They weren't making her
take a שבועה, shvuah but she just jumped in and took the
שבועה. shvuah אמר רב הונא, amar Rav Huna, so רב הונא Rav
Huna said, אוה oh please you can't do that, I'm sorry.
Hey Eddie, Eddie, Eddie, you can't be getting undressed here. I'm just
Eddie. Alright. חי השם צבאות אם נהניתי מכתובתי כלום. chai Hashem Tzevaos
im nehenesi miksuvasi klum.
אמר רב הונא, amar Rav Huna, so רב הונא Rav Huna said,
מודה רב בקופצת. modeh Rav b'kofetzes. You know רב Rav, agrees that
if she jumps in and takes the oath that then it's valid,
okay? So we won't make her take an oath because we can't
be sort of responsible for a false oath, but if she took
an oath, just because oaths are so severe, obviously that would be
valid. So now women have to know that trick, I wonder what
happened trick, whatever, that option. I wonder what happens if she jumped
in and took a נדר? neder Right, would that be good? Maybe
not, maybe a נדר neder for רב Rav would feel wouldn't prove
anything, but an oath does prove something, okay. ההיא דאתאי לקמיה דרבה
בר רב הונא, hahu d'asai l'kamei d'Rabbah bar Rav Huna, somebody came
in front of רבה בר רב הונא. Rabbah bar Rav Huna. אמר
לה, amar lah, said to her, מאי אעביד לך? mai a'avid lach?
Look I can't help you. דרב לא מגבי כתובה לארמלתא, d'Rav lo
magbi kesuvah l'armalta, again quoting the authority of רב, Rav ואבא מארי
לא מגבי כתובה לארמלתא, v'Abba Mari lo magbi kesuvah l'armalta, and my
father, my teacher, did not collect a כתובה kesuvah. for an אלמנה.
And you know my father wouldn't collect it for an אלמנה.
So אמר לה, amar lah, he said to her, הב לי מזוני.
hav li mezoni. Fine, you don't want to allow me to collect
my lump sum payment? I'll go back to living on my husband's
estate and let me be supported by my husband's estate, which is
what was the situation until now. So אמר לה, amar lah, he
said to her, מזוני נמי לית לך. mezoni nami leis lach. No,
I'm sorry, now you've lost your opportunity to be supported by the
estate. דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, De'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, Rav
Yehuda said in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, התובעת כתובתה בבית דין
אין לה מזונות, hatovasa kesuvashah beveit din ein lah mezonos, that once
a woman demands payment of her כתובה, kesuvah. she's no longer supported
by the estate. The reason she's supported by the estate is she's
sort of seen as still like, you know, being like a continuation
of her husband still. She's still living in her husband's house, you
know, she's supported by the estate. As soon as it's clear that
she wants to break away from her dead husband's, you know, family
and establish now her own independence, right, then she's no longer part
of the estate and now she gets her כתובה kesubah payment. So
as soon as you express that desire, you've basically said you're no
longer part of your dead
husband's, you know, sort of family, in his household, I should say,
no longer part of his household. So now you no longer can
be supported by the estate. So she's caught both ways, right?
She gets her כתובה kesubah? at least.
No, but he said that once you demand it, you've basically changed
your identity, you've changed your status. So obviously this is completely unconscionable,
right? So let's take a look. So by the way though, but
it does show you that when רב didn't collect a כתובה kesubah
for the אלמנה, it wasn't... it didn't have to be a complete
disaster because as long as she didn't demand the כתובה, kesubah. she
could at least continue to be supported. She wouldn't be able to
take that money and set off on her own, but at least
it wasn't a complete disaster. Anyway, so now, but now this woman's
completely stuck. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, so he says, אמרה
ליה, amrah leih, she said to him,
אפכוה לכורסיה, afchuah lekursai, your chair should be turned upside down, like,
you know, it was some type of a curse. כי בי תרי
עבדי לי, Kibei srei avdi li, you're going to do to me
like both of these? You're going to פסקן posken one way to
prevent me from collecting my כתובה kesubah and the other way to
prevent me from continuing to get
מזונות? mezonos? So אפכוה לכורסיה, afchuah lekursai, so what they did is
they actually fulfilled her curse. They turned his chair upside down, they
stood it up upside down in order to say like at least
your curse was fulfilled so it won't
actually impact me, you know, impact the whoever the rabbi was. Who
was the rabbi? רבה בר רב הונא. Rabba bar Rav Huna. ואפילו
הכי לא איפרק מחולשא, Va'afilu hachi lo ifrik mechulsha, but he didn't
save himself from getting sick. He got sick as a result of
the curse. Okay, so the sad thing here is, you know, as
I said, is that now you're having these later authorities that are
trumping רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel authority and now they're being quoted and
they're becoming these roadblocks, and it doesn't even sound like it's because
the
reason is seen as a problem, it's just, well, רב said, and
whatever happened to the whole motivation of תיקון עולם? tikkun olam Okay,
so let's take a look. אמר ליה רב יהודה לרב ירמיה ביראה,
Amar leih Rav Yehuda leRav Yirmiyah Bira'a, so רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
said to רב ירמיה ביראה, Rav Yirmiyah Bira'a, אדרה בבית דין. adra
beveit din. So now we're going to get stories where they actually
where they actually
set a woman has to collect her כתובה. ketubah So have her
take a נדר neder in בית דין beit din ואשבעוה חוץ לבית
דין, ve'ashbe'uha chutz leveit din, and have her take a שבועה shvuah?
outside of בית דין. beit din. So now it seems like let's
do both. Okay, we're concerned that it's not going to be fully
proving it, a נדר neder doesn't have the power it used to
have. Do the נדר neder in בית דין beit din and have
the שבועה shvuah outside of בית דין beit din and with the
combination of those two... Now once you're having a שבועה shvuah outside
of בית דין, beit din, why not just just do the שבועה?
shvuah Maybe people felt that that also wasn't fully weighty, meaning it
wasn't... beforehand when we said can you have her take a שבועה
shvuah, out of בית דין, beit din, it seemed like the concern
was would the consequences still be dire? But here it sounds like
the concern over a שבועה shvuah, outside of בית דין beit din
is, is it weighty enough to prove what we needed it to
prove? So here he's sort of saying, do both, have a שבועה
shvuah outside of בית דין, beit din, a נדר neder in בית
דין, beit din, but you gotta find a way that she's going
to collect her כתובה. ketubah Okay. וליתי קלא וליפול באודני, Velesei kalla
velipo be'udni, let the announcement go out and let me hear, let
me hear in my own ear that you've done this. Okay. דבעינא
כהיכי דעביד בה מעשה, Debe'inah keheichi de'avid bamaysa, that I want to
know that you actually have acted on this, that she actually has
collected her כתובה. ketubah Okay. So here he said, this is not
acceptable. Now we gotta find a way that she's going to collect
her כתובה. ketubah So that's nice that the pushback based on obviously
what the whole point of the תיקון עולם was. Okay. גופא, Gufa,
let's now go take a look at that earlier statement. אמר רב
זירא אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Zeira amar Shmuel, לא שנו אלא אלמנה.
lo shanu ella almanah. This is only an אלמנה who has to
who they would not let make a שבועה, shvua. אבל גרושה משביעין
אותה, aval grushah mashbi'inasah, a גרושה grusha could because we're not afraid
that she'll rationalize. גרושה דאדרה לא? Grushah de'adra lo? So now are
we... would that suggest that if we're making... if we didn't make
any special תקנה takkanah for a גרושה, grusha if a גרושה grusha.
made a נדר neder. instead of a שבועה, shvuah presumably it doesn't
work? Presumably she has to make the classic שבועה shvuah that everybody
makes.
Okay. והשלחו מתם, Veha'shalchu mitam, but they sent from there, from ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael back to
בבל, Bavel, איך פלוניתא בת פלוני פלוני, eich plonisa bas ploni ploni,
שרה Sarah the daughter of יעקב, Yaakov, קבילית גיטה, kevilis gitah, she
received her גט get מן... min... From the hand of אחא בר
קידא Akha bar Kida from the hand of אחא בר קידא Akha
bar Kida דמיתקרי איה מרי d'miskarei Ayah Mari whose name who's also
called איה מרי Ayah Mari there's that issue of different names ונדרת
בעשרת פירות שבעולם עליה v'nederet ba'aseres peiros she'ba'olam aleha and she took
a vow and she says that the fruit all the fruit in
the world would be forbidden to her and if דלא קבילה מכתובתה
d'lo kibilis mi'ksubasa that the only thing that she received from her
כתובה ketubah were the following things and she took a vow that
all the fruit in the world would be forbidden for her if
she's lying. What did she admit that she was already prepaid the
כתובה? ketubah אלא גופכא דאחד ela gufka d'achad a certain a coat
וספר תהילים אחד v'sefer Tehillim echad and a scroll of תהילים Tehillim
וספר איוב v'sefer Iyov and a scroll of איוב Iyov ומשלי u'mishalot
and a ספר משלי. sefer Mishlei. So I just want to pause
here for a moment and say that is fascinating right a woman
wanted to collect these things so basically women would learn and I
mean it makes sense like תהילים Tehillim right is דאוונינג davening but
what's really fascinating is איוב Iyov and משלי Mishlei which are you
know like משלי Mishlei is sort of like okay like מוסר-y mussar
right so she's got תנ"ך Tanakh and מוסר mussar that's what they
still teach girls in בית יעקב Bais Yaakov but she's also got
like איוב Iyov which is like philosophy right so you got תנ"ך
Tanakh and you know I mean you got תפילה Tefillah and מוסר
mussar and Jewish philosophy. What? Yeah why not? Because that was belonged
to the husband that was you know obviously scrolls had value right
so that she's taken from her husband's estate okay ומשלי בלויים u'mishalot
bluyim
and they were somewhat like worn out so they weren't like brand
new okay ושמנום בחמישה מנה v'shamnum b'chamisha maneh and we estimated their
value at five מנה. maneh. Okay so that's how much of her
כתובה Kesuvah, has been paid off and she took a vow to
that effect not a שבועה. shvuah וכי שתיתו לקמיכון אגבו לה שאר
v'chishetiyavo l'vachon hagbu es hashaar she is now going to come back
to בבל Bavel and her husband's estate is in בבל Bavel so
make sure she gets paid the remainder of the כתובה. Kesuvah. So
anyway you see that she took it's so great right that little
window into like real life right anyway but now you see that
she took a נדר neder. and this was a case of a
גרושה so it seems like a גרושה can take a נדר. neder
So אמר רב אשי ההוא גט יבמין הוה. Amar Rav Ashi hahu
get yavmim hava. This was a גט יבמין. get yavmim. Now what's
a גט יבמין? get yavmim? So רב אשי Rav Ashi says it
means
that
one of the brothers she was obligated in יבום yibum one of
the brothers gave her a גט get to prevent יבום yibum from
happening him or the other brothers he would have to do חליצה
chalitza and now she's collecting from her dead husband's estate she's really
an אלמנה her husband died. The גט get she got was from
one of her husband's brothers to basically say we're not going to
do יבום yibum we're only going to do חליצה. chalitza. The problem
with that is that תוספות Tosafot says is that you don't collect
from the dead husband's estate until after the חליצה chalitza is done
not the גט get the גט get from the brother-in-law is not
enough you actually need the חליצה chalitza to be done. Okay so
תוספות Tosafot has another version תוספות's Tosafot version is oh
that she actually did יבום yibum with the brother-in-law so she was
now married to the brother-in-law he divorced her. Okay you following this
ראובן Reuven died יהודה Yehuda married her the brother married her then
he divorced her now that she's divorced from יהודה Yehuda where does
she collect her כתובה kesubah, from ראובן's Reuven estate? She goes back
to her first husband's estate that's the nature of יבום yibum that
was considered a continuation of the first husband's you know relationship. So
now that she's going back to collect from ראובן's Reuven estate she
was divorced from יהודה Yehuda but she collects from ראובן's Reuven estate
so that's why it's really a case of an אלמנה not a
case of a גרושה.
Yes you know we've said in various circumstances earlier you know a
woman needed a good lawyer for this she should know what to
say right so here it's as if you know in a way
I mean they're saying she's a righteous woman but also she's saying
things that would make her look good in the eyes of the
court.
You mean that she's taking a vow? Oh you mean that
the תהילים Tehillim
and could be could be it's a good
point
right and she was righteous but
yeah that's a good point that's a good point. Now I do
want to point out that תוספות Tosafot makes an interesting question about
the nature of the נדר. neder תוספות Tosafot is a little bit
bothered with the vow that I won't eat all the fruit in
the world is forbidden to me because fruit by the way doesn't
just mean fruit fruit means like produce. So that's basically a vow
that's impossible to keep. So תוספות Tosafot says so that's a case
where okay you could say fine so she's lying it's a false
vow she transgresses the false vow. There's a גמרא Gemara that says
somebody takes a vow to forbid sleep on himself he gets lashes
right away because he made a vow that's impossible. So maybe that
she's basically saying is if I am lying then I right now
will have made a false vow. But תוספות doesn't sound that way
it doesn't sound like that you can sort of to prove you're
telling the truth say and if I'm lying I'm making this vow
which will have been a transgression. It sounds like that to prove
you're telling the truth you have to live your life through the
restraint or the constraint of this vow right you understand? So if
the nature of the vow is all the fruit in the world
is forbidden to me that's if you had taken that vow you
wouldn't be permissible to eat the fruit you just would have made
a false vow. So that is not enough to prove that you're
honest to say if I'm lying I now will have made a
transgression of a false vow. To prove you're honest you have to
be bound for the rest of your life by the consequences of
your vow okay and that even and if so if you said
like so תוספות says like if so if you said all apples
would be forbidden. to me that means that any time in the
rest of your life every single time you eat an apple you
will transgress again your whole life you will go being bound by
this vow okay so תוספות reads that this vow is of that
type of a nature and that it's something that's possible to live
by and therefore will bind you for your whole life okay so
let's continue now in the גמרא Gemara רבן גמליאל הזקן שתהא נודרת
Rabban Gamliel Hazaken she-tehei noderet
so he made a תקנה takkanah that she should make he can
make she could make a vow אמר רב הונא לא שנו אלא
בשלא ניסית Amar Rav Huna lo shanu ela beshelo niset that's only
true when as long as she has not gotten married okay so
she's going to collect the lump sum payment and now she's probably
looking for a second husband okay so now and so we say
you want to go ahead and collect the כתובה kesubah. fine make
a vow but that ability to make a vow is only as
long as she's not married why אבל ניסית aval niset once she's
married to a second husband אין מדירין אותה ein madirin otah a
vow won't work we don't have her take the vow and therefore
she's stuck she can't collect her כתובה kesubah. why won't a vow
work because ניסית מאי טעמא דמיפר לה בעל niset mai taama d'mefer
lah ba'al
so the גמרא Gemara says one minute so i get it why
is it that once she's married the vow won't work and she
can't collect because if she makes the vow her husband can annul
the vow right yes everybody remember that a husband can annul a
vow that a woman makes whose wife makes so therefore the vow
won't work anymore once she's married so the גמרא Gemara says one
minute if that's true so כי לא ניסית נמי ki lo niset
nami so even if she didn't get married yet and she makes
a vow why does that work לכי מינסבא מיפר לה בעל l'khi
minseva mefer lah ba'al as soon as she gets married then her
husband will find out about it and he'll annul it the day
that they get married so the גמרא Gemara says no no no
that's not a concern אין הבעל מיפר בקודמין ein haba'al mefer bikodmin
the husband cannot annul vows that pre pre-existed the marriage okay so
therefore as long as she makes the vow when she's not yet
married she's going to be bound by it but if she makes
the vow when she is married we're afraid that she will not
be bound by
it if she gets married to a second if she remarries and
has not collected a כתובה then the כתובה is not coming to
her anymore
because she doesn't have this option of the vow now she could
probably go ahead and make a שבועה shvuah like חוץ לבית דין
chutz le-veit din you know she could be קופצת ונשבעת kofetzet ve-nishba'at
but but yes but because she no longer has this option
of making but the עיקר הדין ikkar hadin the כתובה money is
coming to her
she's owed the money she has no way of collecting
there's no instrument for her
exactly exactly okay if she goes ahead and gets
but we assume the יתמי yatmei was not of their own sense
of what's right
they can choose to do whatever they want but you know yes
okay so the גמרא Gemara says וניחוש שמא תזיל לגבי חכם ושרי
לה v'neichosh shema tezil legabei chacham ve-shari lah one minute now that
we're talking about the possibility of getting out of your vow right
so any any woman who makes a vow now again by the
way you read in english there is a difference between a שבועה
shvuah if you have a future-oriented שבועה shvuah you could also get
it annulled right by a like you know by a חכם chacham
i i take a שבועה that i will do X Y and
Z right so then i can get a חכם chacham to annul
it but if it's a past-oriented שבועה i swear right somebody says
that they swear in the name of God that they didn't do
the following or they did the following right so at that moment
you've either transgressed you've made a שבועת שקר shvuat sheker or you
haven't so there's no idea of being released from it by a
חכם chacham so the גמרא Gemara says but if it's this נדר
neder even if she's not married she it can be she can
be released from it right a שבועה she isn't a concern but
now that we've shifted to a נדר she could always be released
from it go to a חכם chacham do a התרת נדרים hatarat
nedarim and get out of it okay so why are we why
does this work
אזל לגבי חכם ושרי לה azal legabei chacham ve-shari lah and he'll
permit it קסבר צריך לפרט את הנדר kasavar tzarich le-faret et haneder
no we believe that you have to detail the vow now detail
when we when we say detail the vow i think what we
normally think that means is give the specifics of what you vowed
you know that i vowed that i would do X because normally
like at התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim we do on ערב ראש השנה
Erev Rosh Hashanah we say i made a vow i made vows
you know free me from them i wish i hadn't made vows
and then we say ואף על פי שאמרו חכמים ve-af al pi
she-amru chachamim the הבא להתיר haba lehatir what is it צריך לפרט
את הנדר tzarich le-faret et haneder
אבל דאנו רבותי כי אפשר לפרטם כי רבים הם aval de-anu rabbotai
ki efshar le-fartam ki rabbim hem but i have to detail it
but there are too many i can't detail it so there the
sense is you're not even telling me what you vowed right say
the specifics of i vowed i wouldn't eat X Y and Z
if A B and C happened but here okay part of לפרט
את הנדר le-faret et haneder is the circumstances and the conditions of
the vow so since you have to give me the circumstances and
the conditions she goes to a חכם chacham and the חכם chacham
says so what made you take this vow that all the fruit
of the world is forbidden to you or that you would never
eat apples well you see i was coming to collect my כתובה
and i swore and i took this vow says oh i can't
release you from that vow right because that whole vow is what
let you collect so since if you hold that you have to
give the details you won't be released from the vow so no
קסבר צריך לפרט את הנדר kasavar tzarich le-faret et haneder you have
to give this details of the circumstances and therefore we're not afraid
i mean we'll assume you'll be truthful to the חכם chacham i
mean it can only go so far you could lie to the
חכם chacham actually that would be an interesting question if you lie
to the חכם chacham and he annulled released you from the vow
based on false information presumably it wouldn't be good it wouldn't be
a good התרה hatarah right i don't know that's an interesting question
right i took a vow about apples never eating apples you lie
what circumstances were, presumably it's צריך לפרט את הנדר tzarich lifrate es
haneder and you lie about it, it's not a good התרה. Hatarah.
Okay, so we're not afraid that you'll be released from the vow
because you'll have to give the circumstances and then you won't be
released from it. All right. So רב נחמן אמר, Rav Nachman amar,
אפילו ניסת, afilu nises,
even if she's married we let her take the vow.
Now ניסת, nises, ודאי מיפר לה בעל, vadai meifer la ba'al, how
could that be? She'll just get her husband to annul it. No.
דמדרינן לה ברבים. demadrinan la berabbim. We make her take a vow
in public. And we'll take a vow when you take a vow
in public, the presumption is it can no longer be annulled by
her husband or by a חכם. Chacham. Now there's going to be
two concepts the גמרא's Gemara going to introduce. One is ברבים berabbim
and the other is על דעת רבים. al da'as rabbim. Now those
are different concepts. ברבים berabbim means once it's a public matter, it's
no longer a private affair. As long as it's a private affair,
I can go ahead and say my כוונה kavanah was X, Y,
Z, my husband can annul it for me, a חכם Chacham can
annul it for me. If it's a public matter, then there's not
like a mechanism, those mechanisms are private mechanisms. Right? There's no, you
know, then it's just something that's owned by like, you know, published
in the newspaper, you can't retract something once it's published in the
newspaper. It's a matter of public record. Okay, the על דעת רבים
al da'as rabbim is a little different. על דעת רבים al da'as
rabbim means based on what, it's like no longer based on my
intent, it's based on what everybody else would be thinking at this
time and would desire for the conditions of the vow. So that's
going to be still fundamentally there's an opening to annul it because
it still is a question about I'm doing it in private but
I'm saying it doesn't just have to do with what's going on
in my mind, it has to do with what everybody else would
want under these circumstances also. And we'll see what that means in
a minute, okay? That probably is a little less clear, we'll get
to that in a minute. But let's first start with ברבים. berabbim.
She does it in public and therefore it's no longer a vow,
it's no longer open for being annulled. Okay, so that solves that
problem. מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you on this: ניסת גובה כתובתה אם
נדרה. nises govah kesuvashah im nadrah. We have a ברייתא Baraisa that
says if she's married she can collect the כתובה, she made a
vow. So you see that that can, that works with, that supports
the latter opinion that you can make it once you're married and
challenges רב הונא Rav Huna who says you can't. So the גמרא
Gemara says מאי לאו נדרה השתא? mai lav nadrah hashta? It sounds
like she made the vow now after she got married and that's
a challenge on רב הונא Rav Huna who says you can't make
a vow when you're married. לא דנדרה מעיקרא, Lo denadrah me'ikara, she
made it originally before she was married. והתניא ניסת נודרת וגובה כתובתה.
v'hatanya nises noderes v'govah kesuvashah. But we have another ברייתא Baraisa that
says if she got married נודרת noderes she makes a vow now
וגובה כתובתה v'govah kesuvashah and collects her כתובה. It's clear that that
supports again this second position. Who is the second one who said
this?
Rav Nachman. It supports רב נחמן Rav Nachman that she can make
a vow and it challenges רב הונא Rav Huna who says she
cannot. The גמרא Gemara says תנאי היא, tannai hi, it's a debate
of תנאים. Tannaim. דאיכא למאן דאמר נדר שהודר ברבים יש לו הפרה
דאיכא למאן דאמר אין לו הפרה. de'ika leman d'amar neder shehudar berabbim
yesh lo hafarah de'ika leman d'amar ein lo hafarah. So bottom line
is, this is what it hinges on. The one that says she
can make a vow once she's married feels that it would be
a public vow. I mean this is really by the way, you
don't need to do anything special to make it a public vow.
She's making it in בית דין. Beis Din. Like that's already a
public vow. So it's a public vow and therefore feels that you
can do it even when you're married. And the one that says,
the ברייתא Baraisa that says you can't do it once you're married
says that doesn't help because we're still, that could still be annulled.
All right, עשרה? asarah?
Maybe by 10? What?
I don't know, I saw maybe, okay, I don't know
what, רש"י Rashi says עשרה. asarah. בעשרה. ba'asarah. Okay, but even so,
you know, it's not hard to achieve the רבים, rabbim, yeah right,
רש"י Rashi says בעשרה. ba'asarah. But it's not hard to achieve the
רבים rabbim once you're in the בית דין Beis Din context, okay?
So all right, described there. Yeah, exactly. All right, waiting room. Anyway,
so we have this debate. Can the woman make it once, a,
why we in general not afraid that she'll get it annulled? Okay,
and that could be because she has to detail it or maybe
there's a scenario of ברבים. berabbim. Can a woman make it once
she's married? There's a debate of תנאים, Tannaim, a debate of רב
הונא Rav Huna and רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, and that debate hinges
on whether if when it's made ברבים, berabbim, by עשרה, asarah, which
we would do and we would make sure she would do, would
that be sufficient to prevent the ability to annul? Okay, yes.
And the mention of ברבים berabbim include women?
Yeah, that's, I don't know, that's always a question. Okay. איבעיא להו,
Iba'ya lehu, they asked the following question: צריך לפרט את הנדר או
אינו צריך? tzarich lifrate es haneder o eino tzarich? Do you have
to detail it? רב נחמן אמר אינו צריך, Rav Nachman amar eino
tzarich, you don't have to, okay, which is interesting because רב נחמן
Rav Nachman was the one that said that she can make it
once, but this is by a חכם Chacham anyway. You don't have
to detail it.
רב פפא אמר צריך, Rav Pappa amar tzarich, you have to. רב
נחמן אמר אינו צריך, Rav Nachman amar eino tzarich, you don't normally
have to detail the
conditions, the circumstances of a vow. Why would
you? I mean why would you want to detail, but what's the
logic that you wouldn't? So רב נחמן אמר אינו צריך, Rav Nachman
amar eino tzarich, you don't normally have to detail the circumstances of
a vow. אם תאמר דצריך, im tomar detzarich, if you said that
you do have to, זימנין דגייז ליה לדיבוריה, zimnin degayiz lei lediburei,
sometimes somebody will cut short his words, won't give all of the
full circumstances, וחכם במאי דשמע מיפר, vechacham bemai deshama meifer, and the
חכם Chacham will only annul it based on what he heard. Right?
So that certainly going back to my idea, if you would lie
it certainly would not be any good. But if somebody would say
it was this and this and this circumstance and you left out
a salient detail, so maybe the annulment... annulment is not a good
annulment because he didn't have all the information. But if you very
much from the outset say we're not going to go into the
details, right? So then I can't be making a mistake based on
my judgment call. It's sort of like whether you say this, do
you list the specific other names the person has? Or do you
just do a כלל klal or whatever names you might have. All
right, so that's the issue within נדרים. nedarim. Now רב פפא אמר
צריך, Rav Papa amar tzarich, you have to, משום מילתא דאיסורא, mishum
milta de-issura, because if you don't give the details, then somebody it'll
lead to a transgression. Meaning somebody might have made a vow like
I know that I have a big יצר הרע yeitzer hara to
go into a, you know, every time I walk by the McDonald's.
So I took a vow that I'm never going to go down
that street with the McDonald's. So now you know I tell the
חכם, chacham, I don't give him any specifics, I just say I
took a נדר not to go down such and such street. So
what he's doing is it's opening me up to an איסור. issur.
I didn't tell him why. The whole point of that vow was
to keep me from doing an איסור. issur. And he doesn't know.
Or I took a vow to allow me to collect a כתובה,
and I'm not going to tell him the details, and then it's
going to allow me to collect money that I don't deserve. So
of course you need to know the details. The חכם chacham can't
release you from a vow without knowing what the consequences of it
were and what the circumstances of it were. Okay.
תנן, tenan, ותניא u-tanya משנה. mishnah. הנושא נשים בעבירה ha-nosei nashim ba-aveira
פסול. pasul. If a כהן kohen marries a woman he's not allowed
to marry, he can't do the עבודה. avodah. עד שידור הנאה, ad
she-yidor hana'ah, until he says that he takes a vow like I
will divorce my wife, and I will, you know, and if I
don't divorce my wife I will,
excuse me, I take a vow that I will not get any
benefit from my wife, you know, and that will sort of force
me to divorce her. Okay, so now my wife is forbidden to
me, I can't sleep with her, I can't get any, she can't
whatever, she can't do any work around the house for me. Okay,
and that's going to compel me to divorce her, right? Because that's
not a viable marriage. Okay, so that's what the כהן kohen does.
And therefore we feel good that he is going to divorce her
right away as soon as he gets around to it. And what
can he do now that he took that vow? ותני עלה, ve-tani
alah, נודר ועובד. noder ve-oved. He takes that vow and look, okay
fine, you need me to divorce her, I'll take this vow to
divorce her, but now I've got to go do the עבודה avodah
in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so he goes, he takes
the vow, he does the עבודה, avodah, יורד, yored, he gets down
from the מזבח, mizbe'ach, ומגרש, u-migaresh, and then he takes care of
it and he divorces her. But we let him do the עבודה
avodah feeling confident that he's going to divorce her because he took
this vow. אי אמרת ei amart אינו צריך לפרט את הנדר, eino
tzarich lefareit es ha-neder,
similar to the question of collecting the כתובה. How do vows ever
be effective in these types of situations if somebody can always go
to a חכם chacham and get out of it without giving the
details, right? So sort of like the question of how does the
vow work for the כתובה. So if you don't have to give
the details, ליזיל לגבי חכם ושרי ליה. leizeil legabei chacham ve-sharei lei.
He'll go to a חכם chacham and he won't give the details
and he'll get a, and he'll get released from it. So what
good do these vows do if you don't need to give the
details? That's exactly the problem. So the גמרא Gemara says the same
answer as before by the woman, דמדירין לה ברבים. de-madirin lah berabbim.
You make her take the vow in public, and if she takes
the vow in public—he, excuse me, takes the vow in public—that will
not be able to be released. Okay, so there are two ways
to prevent the vow from being circumvented. One is that not necessarily,
you have to give the details of it, that's when you go
to a חכם, chacham, and the other is you do it ברבים.
berabbim. And those two ways, one or two of them needs to
work to allow these vows to be effective, you know, to play
the role that they're playing here. Okay, when it's vis-a-vis the husband,
the husband annulling it, right, לפרט את הנדר lefareit es ha-neder doesn't
work anyway, the husband is going to try to help her out
to get her out of it if it's the second husband. So
by the husband it has to be only the solution of ברבים.
berabbim. But in terms of the case about going to the חכם
chacham to be released, it could either be the solution of לפרט
את הנדר lefareit es ha-neder or that if it's ברבים berabbim it
cannot be annulled. Okay, and now we, so you know what, we'll
just end with this and we'll pick up tomorrow to continue to
explore this issue of what type of a vow can or cannot
be annulled.